Guide to the Dennison I. Rusinow Papers, 1963-2000 UA.90.F84
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dennison I. Rusinow Papers
1963-2000
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rusinow, Dennison I.
UA.90.F84
3 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
This collection contains the papers of Dennison I. Rusinow, adjunct professor of history, research professor in the Center for Russian and East European Studies at the University of Pittsburgh and preeminent scholar of the former-Yugoslavia. The focus of the collection is the late professor's research materials and margin notes. These documents offer a perspective of the Cold War from Yugoslavia's non-aligned vantage point. Additionally, Rusinow's own thoughts, ideas and questions can often be found along the margins of the research itself. The political pamphlets and Tito box set are also unique. Both sets are original documents from Southeastern Europe collected during the late professor's professional career abroad. Textual documents such as transcripts, manuscripts, correspondence, reports and course materials compose the majority of the collection, with the exception of a few sets of photographs and the Josip Broz Tito box set.
Biography
Dennison Rusinow was a highly accomplished journalist, scholar and professor. In 1963, he began a 25-year career with the American Universities Field Staff (AUFS), as associate for Southeastern Europe and later associate director. His book on the political economic history of the former Yugoslavia, The Yugoslav Experiment, 1948-1974, published in 1977, earned him international acclaim as an expert on the former multi-ethnic nation. Before retiring in 2000, Rusinow had devoted the last 12 years of his professional life to the University of Pittsburgh as both an adjunct History professor and research professor at the University Center for International Studies.
Born on October 29, 1930, Rusinow grew up in St. Petersburg, Florida. At Duke University, he received a B.A. in Philosophy and History, graduating first in his class in 1952. As a Rhodes Scholar, he earned a second B.A. from New College at Oxford University. Immediately following graduation, he served a 3-year stint as an intelligence officer in the U.S. Navy. Returning to England after his service in the Navy, he earned a M.A. from New College at Oxford University in 1959. Finally, in 1963, he received his Doctorate of Philosophy from St. Anthony's College at Oxford while simultaneously serving a fellowship at the Institute of Current World Affairs, which included studying in Vienna and Belgrade.
Rusinow devoted more than 40 years of scholarship to Southeastern Europe. His areas of expertise included ethnic nationalism in Yugoslavia, the Cyprus conflict and Marshall Tito's regime. Prior to joining the faculty at Pittsburgh, he served as: adjunct professor of history at Dartmouth College in 1976, lecturer in international affairs at California Institute of Technology in 1970, lecturer in Balkan and Italian Studies at the Institute for Mediterranean Studies in Rome from 1969 to 1977 and adjunct assistant professor of history at Michigan State University in 1965.
In addition to his accomplishments in the university classroom, Rusinow's total scholarship included five books, numerous newspaper and journal articles as well as contributions to several edited volumes on the subject of Eastern Europe.
Following his retirement from the University of Pittsburgh in 2000, Rusinow took up residence back in St. Petersburg, Florida. On January 20, 2004, he died at the age of 73.
Scope and Content Notes:
This collection documents Rusinow's professional career as both an associate for the American University Field Staff and as a university professor. Numerous types of textual documents such as correspondence, research, seminar transcripts, survey data, newspaper clippings, syllabi, resumes, presentation fliers, hand-written notes, un-translated materials, course materials, scholarly articles, manuscripts and other miscellaneous documents make up the actual content of the collection. The dates of said documents range from as early as 1963, when he began working for the AUFS, up through 2000, when he retired from the University of Pittsburgh.
The collection has been organized into three series according to general topic. The first series contains Rusinow's research for some of the 76 AUFS reports he produced between 1963 and 1991. Personal documents and materials such as correspondence, resumes and seminar materials compose the second series.
The final series is devoted to Rusinow's career in academia. The documents in this series emphasize his term as professor at the University of Pittsburgh.
Arrangement
Series I. Research Materials
Series II. Personal, Dennison I. Rusinow
Series III. Academic Career and Course Materials
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Books and papers donated by Mary Rusinow in July 2003. Papers transferred to Archives in February 2005.
Previous Citation
Dennison I. Rusinow Papers, 1963-2000, UA.90.F84, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Yugoslavia; Nationalism -- Baltic States -- History; Cold War -- Propaganda; Cold War; University of Pittsburgh; Faculty papers; Yugoslavia -- Foreign relations -- 1945-1980 -- Sources; Yugoslavia -- Ethnic relations; Rusinow, Dennison I.; Kukučín, Martin; Tito, Josip Broz
- Research Materials, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The files in this series date from 1963 to 1968 and contain Rusinow's accumulated research. This research was likely used in the production of Rusinow's reports on Yugoslavia for the American University Field Staff. Radio Free Europe background analyses, current regional events reports as well as translations of eastern European media served as the principal sources for his AUFS research.
  - Ports, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 01-03)
  - Communes, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Media & Science, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Arts, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 06-07)
  - Economic Reform, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 08-09)
  - Security Service, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Nationalities, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Skopje Earthquakes, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - Foreign Policy: Poland, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Foreign Policy: Comecon Bloc, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Foreign Policy: U.S.S.R., 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Foreign Policy: Czechoslovakia, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Foreign Policy: Hungary & Rumania, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Foreign Policy: Bulgaria, GDR, China, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Communism, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 05-06)
  - Slovenia, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Personal, Dennison I. Rusinow, II.
  Dating from 1984 to 2000, this series concerns itself with Rusinow's professional activities outside of teaching and journalism. Manuscripts, correspondence, resumes, hand-written notes, seminar materials and scholarly articles are all included within this series. The folders of correspondence primarily deal with professional matters, such as thank you notes, contract matters, and administrative issues but also some personal notes between friends and colleagues included as well.
  - Correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Articles about Rusinow, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rusinow CVs, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Revolution of Westernization", undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hand-written Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Political Landscape of a Communist Nation in Transition: Slovenia, 1988-1989" by Peter Jambrek (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Uncertain Path: The Problem of Democratic Transition and Consolidation in Slovenia" by Rudolf Martin Rizman, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "The Macedonian Question's Shifting Face" by S. Victor Papacosma, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "The Yugoslav Labyrinth" by E.A. Hammel (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Serbian Intellectuals and the National Question: 1961-1991" by Audrey H. Budding, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Steering Committee of the International Conference on the Former Yugoslavia Report, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "The European Union and the Challenge of Enlargement" by Ronald H. Linden, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Yugoslavia's Hyperinflation, 1993-1994" by James Lyon, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The War against Croatia: A Chronology of Aggression, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Political Pamphlets from Eastern European Countries, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Yugoslav Federation Agreement, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Un-translated Material, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Survey Data, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
  - Mostar e Dintorni, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Martin Kukučín, 1860-1928, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Transcript of Yugoslav Conference, Smithsonian Institution Wilson Center, September 4-6, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Transcript of Yugoslav Conference, National Identity Seminars, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 02-03)
  - Transcript of Yugoslav Conference, Nationalism Seminars (Pitt), 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Transcript of Yugoslav Conference, Nationalism Seminar (Ohio State), 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Transcript of Yugoslav Conference, Lectures & Meetings, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Transcript of Yugoslav Conference, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Academic Career and Course Materials, III.
  This series contains materials from Rusinow's second career as a university professor and researcher. The bulk of the documents relate to Rusinow's thirteen years of teaching the University of Pittsburgh. In addition to course syllabi, much of his original course materials for his classes are available. The Tito box set, found in Box 4, contains propaganda posters and blown-up photographs documenting the Yugoslav leader's life and accomplishments.
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1.
    - University of Pittsburgh Materials, 1987-1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Course Evaluations, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Lecture Flyers, 1988-2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - HIS 2005/2211 Eastern Central European Readings, 1990-1998 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - HIS 1000 Uses and Abuses of History, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - HIS 1046 Nationalism and Communism, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - HIS 103/PS 124 Nationalism and Communism, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - HIS 1005 Yugoslavia, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - HIS 1006 Yugoslavia, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - HIS 1005 The Idea of Europe, 1993-1998 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - HIS 12 Europe's Unities and Diversities, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - HIS 033/733 East European Civilization, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - HIS 7200 Eastern Europe, 1992 - 1993 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - PS 103 Eastern Europe in World Politics, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - HIS 139/PS 112 Politics of Eastern Europe, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - HIS 037/737 20th Century Eastern Europe, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - HIS 1240/PS 1346 Political Eastern Europe, 1991-1997 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - HIS 1042 Nationalism, 1991 - 1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - HIS 933/733 Unknown, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous Course Materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
    - Miscellaneous Syllabi, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Other Academic Institutions, 2.
    - Dartmouth College, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Center for Mediterranean Studies, Rome1970-1977 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Josip Broz Tito Box Set, 3.
    - Josip Broz Tito Box Set, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)